{"tossups": [{"question": "While it was master-planned by a whisky manufacturer, the town of Walkerville became the first major center of this industry in Canada. During the 1920s, dozens of largely inefficient Canadian companies in this industry like Gray-Dort, Russell, and McLaughlin benefited from high tariffs. Thousands of jobs in this industry were created after Prime Minister Pearson and President Johnson signed a 1965 agreement which removed tariffs and guaranteed levels of production. That (*) \u201cPact\u201d governing this industry was an important predecessor to NAFTA, which did not end the \u201cbranch-plant\u201d system that allowed American companies in this industry to cheaply manufacture in Canada. While founded in South Bend, Hamilton, Ontario was the last place to manufacture for Studebaker, a major company in this industry. For 10 points, name this industry which in the post-World War II period employed thousands of people in Windsor, Ontario.", "answer": "automotive (accept equivalents like car or vehicles)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Hill-men from this mountain range aided another kingdom in a battle that resulted in the death of Argeleb I. A noblewoman was rescued from torture by her twin sons after being attacked while passing through this mountain range\u2019s Redhorn Gate. A chieftain from Mt. Gram in this range was decapitated during the Battle of Greenfields, his head apocryphally being sent 100 yards into a rabbit hole in the process. A ruler later known as the \u201cDeathless\u201d founded a kingdom in this mountain range near where he saw his reflection \u201ccrowned\u201d with seven stars while looking into the (*) Mirrormere. Gandalf traveled from the roots of Mt. Zirakzigil in this range to its peak during his fight with Durin\u2019s Bane. For 10 points, identify this mountain range of central Middle-Earth which contains a former Dwarven kingdom known during the time of the Fellowship as Moria.", "answer": "Misty Mountains (accept Mountains of Mist or Hithaeglir)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Historians have criticized Noel Perrin\u2019s influential book that describes how a country \u201cgave up\u201d these objects, noting that many of them were not confiscated by its government because they were viewed as tools. David L. Howell, in a \u201csocial history\u201d of these objects, describes how a variety of them called odoshi were commonly used by farmers. A variety of these objects used during the Sengoku period, named after the (*) Tanegashima clan, were used in Japan centuries after they were abandoned in the rest of the world. These objects, which were first adopted from a \u201csnap\u201d Portuguese design, were used by Oda Nobunaga to defeat Takeda Shingen\u2019s cavalry at the battle of Nagashino, and designs using flint were not adopted during Japan\u2019s period of isolation. For 10 points, identify these weapons that dramatically changed warfare in feudal Japan by requiring considerably less experience than a bow, which were fired with a match.", "answer": "guns (accept firearms or matchlocks; accept tanegashima before read)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Thomas Guthrie and John Pounds set up the \u201cragged\u201d variety of these places. The \u201cSandon\u201d and \u201cMundella\u201d acts followed an act drafted by William Forster in 1870 regulating these places. The \u201cLancasterian System\u201d was implemented in some of these places, which were often administered by charitable institutions as the \u201cBlue Coat\u201d variety of these places. The \u201cTripartite\u201d system which regulated the administration of these places was put in place by the 1944 Butler Act, and that system was made obsolete by the creation of the (*) \u201ccomprehensive\u201d type of these places. Margaret Thatcher became known as the \u201cMilk Snatcher\u201d following her abolition of the milk dole at these places, two of which are named Rugby and Harrow. For 10 points, name these institutions that provide primary and secondary forms of education.\u00a0", "answer": "British Schools (do not accept or prompt on \u201cUniversities\u201d, \u201cColleges\u201d, or other answers indicating a higher education institution)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Josephine Gabler and Ada Martin operated a business around this practice in Chicago in the 1930\u2019s which required its customers to be blindfolded. The Hogan Amendment was the first in a series of proposed legislation that sought to regulate this practice. An organization founded to promote this practice advertised with signs telling people to \u201cCall Jane\u201d. Public opinion about this practice was noticeably altered when Sherri Chessen sought it after taking (*) thalidomide. In the absence of specific legislation governing it, in the early 19th century this practice\u2019s legality was defined by when it happened in relation to quickening. Ted Kennedy opposed Robert Bork\u2019s nomination to the Supreme Court with a speech that claimed that with him on the bench, this practice would be performed in \u201cback alleys\u201d. For 10 points, name this practice, women\u2019s choice of using which was protected with Roe v. Wade.", "answer": "abortion (prompt on \u201cbirth control\u201d, \u201cfamily planning\u201d, or similar answers)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The GAR and \u0160IM signs came to be used to depict materials and tools used to produce this good. Dug cavities and stone slates in the Raqefet Cave are the earliest historical evidence of the creation of this good, which was used during rituals by the Natufian culture. A tablet found from Uruk, the oldest inscription describing the payment of workers, records the use of this good in lieu of currency also found in the Code of Urukagina. Scholars like Brian Hayden and Patrick McGovern have theorized that agricultural civilization emerged not to grow (*) food, but instead to support demand for this good. Using material called bippar, priestesses of the goddess Ninkasi created this good, and the Hymn to Ninkasi is an early recipe for creating it. The first production of this good in the Fertile Crescent roughly coincided with production of bread, as they both use domesticated cereal grains. For 10 points, identify this good, a drink critical to the early Mesopotamian diet with domesticated barley.", "answer": "beer (prompt on \u201calcohol\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A popular explanation for the origin of the sport of tent pegging is that it was invented for use against these animals. Diodorus Siculus wrote that Marcus Atilius Regulus had his eyelids cut off before being killed by one of these animals. The Legio V Alaudae adopted one of these animals as their emblem after the Battle of Thapsus. In his Stratagems of War, Polyaenus claimed that the residents of Megara used (*) flaming pigs to counter the use of these animals in a siege of the city. According to Pliny the Elder, these animals were first known to the Romans as \u201cLucanian Oxen\u201d after the Battle of Heraclea against Pyrrhus. The use of these animals was countered by allowing them to pass harmlessly through the Roman army at the Battle of Zama. For 10 points, name these largest extant land animals, which Hannibal famously brought across the Alps.", "answer": "elephants (accept pachyderms or other scientific names)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Though likely not producing millions of bushels as estimated by Berthold Laufer, 16th century farmers in this country\u2019s relatively unproductive southeast grew small amounts of maize in mountainous areas. A memoir partially titled Dreams of Splendor describes extravagant dinners eaten in pre-modern restaurants in this country, where the first restaurant menus were used. Inspiring a modern idiom, a ruler of this country held a massive, three day banquet with over 300 dishes of (*) imperial palace cuisine on his 66th birthday. An early agricultural system that featured eight plots of private farmland surrounded by a plot communally cultivated for a land-owning aristocrat was called the well-field system, while the government distributed land to families proportional to their size in the equal-field system. For 10 points, identify this country, where the independent advent of agriculture led to the early Xi\u00e0 and Sh\u0101ng dynasties.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of China (accept Zh\u014dnggu\u00f3 or PRC)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The parallels between Christia\u00a0\u00a0\u00a0 n saints and this culture\u2019s hero Bochica were seen by some early Spanish colonizers as evidence of Pre-Columbian Christian evangelism in the area. This culture\u2019s g\u00fcecha warriors were reported by an early Spanish chronicler to not produce their own bows and arrows, but took them from captured Panche warriors. This culture expanded upon the ritual and astronomical site of El Infiernito following the Herrera Culture. In 1899, Hartley Knowles formed a company for the sole purpose of finding the artifacts that this culture had ceremonially sunk into (*) Lake Guatavita; during those ceremonies, a leader called the zipa would be covered in gold dust to offer the gods golden artifacts in the middle of the lake. For 10 points, identify this culture of the Colombian Andes, whose skill in gold working was likely the origin of the myth of El Dorado.", "answer": "Muisca people (accept Muisca Confederation; accept Chibcha people)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A monument to an event in this process is surrounded by a wall with 64 wagons on it, commemorating a skirmish during this process in which one side utilized a laager. A treaty made to facilitate this process was recovered from the corpse of one of its leaders who had earlier been betrayed and killed. Despite receiving over 20 wounds, Johanna van der Merwe survived the Weenen (VAY-nen) Massacre during this process. A leader opposed to this process exclaimed \u201cKill the wizards!\u201d to command his troops to massacre a delegation led by (*) Piet Retief. After the Battle of Blood River, Mpande joined with the participants in this process to usurp his brother Dingane and ally the Zulu with the newly arrived white settlers. For 10 points, identify this process, the migration of many Boers from the Cape Colony into the interior of Southern Africa.", "answer": "Great Trek (accept Die Groot Trek, De Grote Trek, or Voortrek)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Former members of the Liberation Army of the South, such as Genovevo de la O and Gildardo Maga\u00f1a, were rehabilitated by this man. As a farmer, this man made his fortune selling chickpea harvesters in the Mayo Valley. This man\u2019s arm was blown off at the Battle of Le\u00f3n, which followed a battle where he effectively used trenches and machine guns against generals like Felipe Angeles. Secretary of Education Jos\u00e9 Vasconcelos served under this leader. As a general, this man decisively won the battles of Aguas Calientes and (*) Celaya against Pancho Villa, and he was assassinated by the Roman Catholic fanatic Jos\u00e9 de Le\u00f3n Toral. This first president of the Sonoran dynasty and formulator of the Plan of Agua Prieta overthrew Venustiano Carranza to achieve his highest position, and he was succeeded by Plutarco Calles [cay-EZ]. For 10 points, name this President of Mexico from 1920 to 1924.\u00a0", "answer": "\u00c1lvaro Obreg\u00f3n Salido", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A paper by Soffer et al found that these objects from the eastern end of their distribution featured either woven caps, jewelry, or both, while those at the western end do not have either. Andr\u00e9 Leroi-Gourhan used the term \u201clozenge composition\u201d to describe the unnatural proportions of these objects, which a paper by LeRoy McDermott argued reflect the perspective of their creators viewing their own bodies. The first of these objects to be discovered was given a name to contrast it with Classical statues in the (*) pudica pose; that object is a relatively late example, having been made by a Magdalenian culture. Perhaps the most famous of these objects was found in 1908 near the town of Willendorf, Austria. For 10 points, identify these works of Upper Paleolithic art depicting women with accentuated breasts and hips, commonly named after the Roman goddess of love.", "answer": "Venus figurines", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A battle won by a member of this family may have happened in part due to the translator Felipillo\u2019s intentional mistranslation between the combatants. A member of this family joined with Francisco de Carvajal in a failed rebellion, which ended at the Battle of Jaquijahuana [hah-kee-hah-wah-nah]. A city was founded by a member of this family after his first choice for a seat of government, Jauja [\u201chow\u201d-hah], was deemed too isolated. A member of this family was killed by the troops of (*) \u201cEl Mozo\u201d. The Battle of Las Salinas was fought between the forces of this family against the former captor of two of them, Diego de Almagro. The rejection of chicha by his side and of the Bible by the other led a member of this family to fight, and win, the Battle of Cajamarca. Hernando, Gonzalo, and Francisco were all part of which family, which led the conquest of the Inca Empire?", "answer": "Pizarro family", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Historian Rudi Paul Litner proposed that the rise of this empire came from tribal organization and the assimilation of diverse populations, in opposition to the popular \u201choly war\u201d theory proposed by Paul Wittek. Several members of the \u00c7andarl\u0131 [chan-dar-loo] family advised rulers of this empire. The first of few historical records of the founder of this empire was his victory at the Battle of Bapheus. Early upper classes in this empire were made of kasaker military judges and (*) timariot calvarymen. During the almost forty year rule of the second ruler of this empire, was advised by his half-brother Aleaddin on a new military system after he captured the city of Nicomedia. In a mythical story, the founder of this empire had a dream of a tree sprouting from his navel and shading the world; that ruler\u2019s grandson founded the devshirme system and was slain at the Battle of Kosovo. For 10 points, identify this empire that started as a small state in western Anatolia, founded by Osman I.", "answer": "Ottoman Empire", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This activist lived the last fifty years of her life in England, where she gave lectures such as \u201cThe Human Body, the Temple of God.\u201d At the age of 15, this activist escaped a medicine show her con man father forced her to perform in, and she later married Colonel James Harvey Blood. Together with her sister Tennessee Claflin, this person founded a \u201cWeekly\u201d paper. This activist\u2019s role as a spiritual advisor to (*) Cornelius Vanderbilt helped her found the first female brokerage firm on Wall Street. This activist wrote a massively controversial expose of Henry Ward Beecher\u2019s adultery that led to the passage of the Comstock Act. Her advocacy of free love caused former allies like Susan B. Anthony to withdraw their support during an election in which she was nominated by the Equal Rights Party. For 10 points, name this activist, who in 1872 became the first woman to run for president.\u00a0", "answer": "Victoria Woodhull", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Ottoman traveler Evliya \u00c7elebi (chay-\u201clay-bee\u201d) wrote with admiration of how many Jewish slaves this state captured, selling each for the price of a tobacco pipe. The founder of this state adopted a golden trident on a blue field as his dynasty\u2019s coat of arms, a symbol known as the taraq tam\u011fa. An Alexander Pushkin poem fictionalizes the death of the favorite concubine of a ruler of this state and the fountain he erected in her honor in his palace in the capital of Bakhchisarai. A ruler of this state earned the epithet Tahti Alan, or \u201cTaker of the Throne,\u201d after burning (*) Moscow. This state ruled by the Giray (\u201cghee-rye\u201d) dynasty was made independent from Ottoman rule by the Treaty of Kuchuk-Kainarji until annexed by Russia in 1783. For 10 points, identify this state, the longest-lived successor to the Golden Horde, named after a peninsula in the Black Sea.", "answer": "Crimean Khanate", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A golden statue found in a river in this modern-day country was identified by H. Otley Beyer as the Siavite goddess Tara, which suggests Hinduism was prominent there before the spread of Islam. Distinguished by whether they lived on or off their master\u2019s property, the alipin were the lowest social class during this modern-day country\u2019s feudal period. River deltas in this country were home to city-state-like polities called bayans, ruled by a Datu, that were made of several social groups called (*) barangays. Remnants of boats called balangay is evidence of extensive gold trade of Rajahnate of Butuan in the southern part of this country. Sharif ul-H\u0101shim founded a polity centered in this country that would become infamous for pirate attacks with small, fast boats on colonial ships. That polity, the Sultanate of Sulu, led the Moro raids on ships not following a trade route that sent spices east from a port in this country in exchange for silver from Acapulco. For 10 points, identify this country in Southeast Asia colonized by Spain several decades after it was the site of Magellan\u2019s death.", "answer": "Republic of the Philippines", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s most famous conquests were aided by the efforts of Pierre Gibault in enlisting local support. This man refused assistance from Young Tobacco because he feared his troops might be mistaken for Kickapoo soldiers. Simon Girty was one of the commanders who ambushed the forces led by Archibald Lochry before they could meet up with this man. POW Leonard Helm delivered Henry Hamilton\u2019s surrender to this man after his capture of Fort Sackville. James Wilkinson was a vocal critic of this man\u2019s (*) alcohol abuse late in his career. This man weakened the British presence on the Wabash and Mississippi Rivers by taking towns like Vincennes and Kaskaskia. For 10 points, who was this foremost American military commander in the Northwest Territories during the Revolutionary War and the older brother to the man who co-led an expedition with Merriwether Lewis?", "answer": "George Rogers Clark (prompt on just \u201cClark\u201d because of his more famous younger brother)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "John II of Brabant was besieged in Genappe castle for sheltering Jews by an army of the poor on their way to this city. A different city was depicted in a medieval map as a widow in black when Raymond Bertrand de Got moved from it to this city. Geoffrey Boucicaut (\u201cboo-see-COE\u201d) besieged a building in this city for five years before Pedro Mart\u00ednez de Luna escaped. An ecumenical council in this city excommunicated Raymond VI of Toulouse. (*) Laura de Noves, believed to be the \u201cLaura\u201d of Petrarch\u2019s works, was a native of this city. The potential loss of power that the War of the Eight Saints could have created for this city led to the accession of Robert of Geneva as Clement VII, whom many countries recognized over Gregory XI in Rome. For 10 points, name this southern French city home to the Papacy from 1309-1376.", "answer": "Avignon", "category": "History"}, {"question": "ANSWER: Avignon <AF> \u00a0 20. Description acceptable Researchers from Australia have proposed that this process relied on corridors like the Sangha River Interval, and was delayed by rainforests. Historian Christopher Ehret has characterized the time period defined by this process a \u201cclassical age\u201d and identifies two distinct branches within it. The eastern area affected by this process correlates to the use of pottery in the Urewe tradition. Rock art in the Tsodilo Hills and the Mangolong Cave depicting cattle and men with shields may be evidence that this process influenced hunter-gathers to adopt limited amounts of animal raising. Archaeologists estimate that this process began in 1000 B.C. in central (*) Cameroon, and traditionally historians have traced it with the use of iron and the cultivation of yams. In South Africa, this process stopped when land unsuitable to agriculture was reached, and it likely did not \u201cpush\u201d the Khoisan people into the Kalahari. For 10 points, identify this process, a migration that took place over centuries that spread the namesake branch of Niger-Congo languages across Southern Africa.", "answer": "the Bantu expansion (accept any answer indicating the spread of Bantu peoples)", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}